[SPEAKER_02]: Let's make sure they're right.
[SPEAKER_02]: August 28, 1898 in St. Louis?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: St. Louis, Missouri.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you come from a ball-playing family?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dad didn't play ball?
[SPEAKER_02]: A bunch of house painters.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where'd your talent first emerge?
[SPEAKER_02]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_02]: You play in high school or Sandlot?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I never went to high school.
[SPEAKER_01]: My father wanted me to be a house painter too, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I wanted to be a ball player.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I only went to about the fifth grade public school.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I always did contend that I could have went to the sixth grade, but I didn't want to pass the old man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Embarrassed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I was satisfied.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had many jobs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was with Connie Mack in 1960.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, did you play ball in St. Louis?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, St. Louis Screw Company, the old St. Louis Screw Company in the Municipal League.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I played for the Campbell Auto Supply Company.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a matter of fact, I cheated a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the only time I ever cheated in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: I played on Saturdays under the name of Charlie Graham for the St. Louis Screw Company.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on Sundays, I played under my own name, Charlie Grimm,
[SPEAKER_01]: Camelotto Supply Company.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how I got my start.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was signed by Philadelphia Athletics in 1916.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have a scout there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meyer Thomas, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, Meyer, the old catcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the old catcher, Connie Meyer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I joined them, played about three months there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that in 1917, as you know, the war, they sent me to Durham, but I never played in Durham.
[SPEAKER_01]: I only played one year in the minor leagues, and that was Little Rock, Arkansas.
[SPEAKER_01]: What year was that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That'd be in 1918.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the fall of 1918, I was sold to the Pittsburgh Pirates.
[SPEAKER_02]: What happened with your Connie Mack arrangement?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did they let you go?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I was a free agent.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were pretty young then, too, buddy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was about 16 or 17 years old.
[SPEAKER_02]: How'd you like playing with Connie?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he was a great man.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a great man.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a matter of fact, the three months
[SPEAKER_01]: that I spent there was quite a baseball education for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was just a wonderful man.
[SPEAKER_01]: He never called anybody by their first name.
[SPEAKER_01]: That included fellas like Jimmy Dykes and Amos Strunk, who were on that 1916 ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll call them all son.
[SPEAKER_02]: He already was old enough to be their father, I guess.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh my, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: There were a lot of those fellas on that club.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who was their first baseman?
[SPEAKER_01]: Stuffy McGinnis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did he give you any tips?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I watched him, really the man that I followed when I was in St. Louis as a kid was Hal Chase.
[SPEAKER_01]: He took quite an interest in me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he was my idol.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was called the greatest fielding first baseman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, he was, he was great.
[SPEAKER_02]: He had some other flaws though.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he got into a lot of trouble.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he could really field.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he was a great fielding first baseman, not a bad hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he knew all the fundamentals of the game and he took a lot of interest in me and around old Robinson Field and Sportsman's Park in St. Louis and he became my idol.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course as I played ball in the National League all my life why Babe Ruth was my idol because we became real good friends as I got a little older.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, George's sister was pregnant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a great ball player, but I was established then in the National League.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never saw much of George, only around St. Louis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, how did the Cardinals get you then in 1918?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I just went there in 1918.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the war year, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went there and just ranched.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ricky was the general manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jack Hendricks was the manager and I just hung around the ballpark there and didn't get into any games at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're the ones that sent me to Little Rock.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I played one year for Little Rock and was sold to the Pirates in the fall of 1918.
[SPEAKER_02]: They had some scouts looking at you or just how did that develop?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yeah, that developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bobby Wallace, quite a few scouts.
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you think of Branch Rickey?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as time went on, I admired the man.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought he was Mr.
[SPEAKER_01]: Baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a great fundamentalist.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course, if you wanted a little money off of him or something, he'd make you cry with all the bad deals that happened to him through his baseball life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mentally, to me, he was Mr.
[SPEAKER_01]: Baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: If anybody followed him right on down the line and followed on his line, he became a good, smart baseball man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who managed the Pirates when you went up there in 19- Well, they had George Gibson, Hugo Besdag, the old, I think, the old football coach, and Bill McKechnie.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had quite a few managers there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who did you succeed as first baseman?
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the Grimes boys.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ray Grimes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ray Grimes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who else is on that team?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you remember that team very well?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they had George with it, Barnhart, Wagner was through with it, Max Carey, Honest Wagner was just going out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was a good friend of Honest as he took a liking to him too.
[SPEAKER_02]: They say when rookies first come up, the old timers don't give much help or break because they're taking their jobs away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, a fellow like Wagner, they've been at the end of the rope and
[SPEAKER_01]: And all you had to do was listen to them a little bit, and they'd take a liking to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, it took me a long time to get in the batting cage, because they wouldn't leave you in there in those days.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't leave you in there at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You had to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a matter of fact, I have a catching mitt I caught batting practice in spring training, just to have something to do with the ball club.
[SPEAKER_02]: You went to spring training in 19?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, Hot Springs, Arkansas.
[SPEAKER_02]: That must have been a big thrill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was my first big thrill of baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did they give you much money that first year?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just got, I think it was somewhere around $2,500 a year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, how were the Pirates that year?
[SPEAKER_01]: How'd they do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we were right up there once I became a regular first baseman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always in contention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And football players like Carson Bigby, Max Carey,
[SPEAKER_01]: And George Whitted, Cotton Tierney, Waller Schmidt, and I had a good pitch in staff, Lee Meadows, Babe Adams, all those old timers were great pitchers.
[SPEAKER_02]: When did you start playing basketball?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I started that when I was a kid.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a matter of fact, I had a lot of fun all through my baseball career.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was a relaxed ball player, and when I managed, I relaxed my ball player.
[SPEAKER_02]: You had a number of combos throughout your career.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a matter of fact, we had as good a band as the old Gas House gang.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought we did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who were some of them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Barney Fryberg was one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did he play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Third base.
[SPEAKER_01]: He played the mandolin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cliff Heathcote, the old outfielder, he played a guitar.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hack Miller played a guitar.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I played my banjo.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we had a guy in the club who had a pretty good voice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was a pitcher, Al Carlson.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What was this Paderewski story?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that Paderewski story was something we were trained at Pazza Robles out in California.
[SPEAKER_01]: I used to, after workout, I used to practice my banjo a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there was a knock at the door one day, and Andy Lux, our trainer, was right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knock came in the door, and it was
[SPEAKER_01]: who was probably Paderewski's secretary, knocked on the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Andy went to the door, and he says, this gentleman there told me that Mr. Paderewski's upstairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't know who Paderewski was.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, Mr. Paderewski's right above us here in his room.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's having his afternoon nap and asked you to quiet down or else quit playing that banjo.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I began.
[SPEAKER_01]: quit, and about a couple days later after practice, I had a little time lying down, and Padruski was a great pianist, as you know, and I heard this beautiful flow of music coming out of the window on the second floor.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went to living on the first floor, and I called up Andy Lashaw to come down, and I said, would you mind going up and knocking on Mr. Padruski's door and telling Mr. Charlie Grimm, first baseman for the Pittsburgh Pirates,
[SPEAKER_01]: is taking his afternoon's nap and ask him to quit playing on the piano.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: I finally met the man and he got quite a kick out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How'd you like McKechnie?
[SPEAKER_01]: Bill McKechnie was a great guy.
[SPEAKER_01]: A lot of critics thought he was too Pollyannic but
[SPEAKER_01]: I followed his way of managing quite a bit, but I liked to play for Bill.
[SPEAKER_01]: I played for Bill for quite a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the best manager I played for was Joe McCarthy on the coach in 1929.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why was that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he was more of a... he used psychology.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by this time I became a character like Gabby Harden and Hack Wilson, and he treated everybody
[SPEAKER_01]: Psychologically, he treated each individual the way he should be treated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the way I phrased myself around managing my ballplayers when I became manager of the Chicago Cubs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tell me, during those 20s while you were with Fitzgerald and then over with the Cubs, did you think you might want to be a manager someday?
[SPEAKER_01]: Never gave it a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Joan McCarthy made the captain out of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I took those chores over for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it took about, oh, I guess a year and a half, two years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pardon me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I caught up with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought I was getting pretty smart myself, but I wasn't looking for anybody's job.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Roger Hornsby took over McCarthy's job after the 1929 World Series.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had no visions at all of managing the Cubs until
[SPEAKER_01]: Ornsby got in trouble with Bill Beck, Sr., who was president of the Chicago Cubs at that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we lost a tough ball game in Brooklyn.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we went from Brooklyn over to Philadelphia to open up a series.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Bob Lewis, our traveling secretary, came down to my room.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, come on up to my room.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bill Beck wants to have a talk chat with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I went up to the room, waited for his call in Bob Lewis's room, and he asked me if I wanted to manage the club.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, well, what happened to Hornsby?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, we're letting Hornsby go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, then I'll take the job.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just out of the blue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just out of the blue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we went from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was 1944.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in 1945, not 45, in 1932, we won the pennant in 1932 and played the Yankees and never won a ball game off of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, when you took over, the team was always in second place, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So they weren't really that far out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greatest break a guy ever had in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I looked at that ball club and everybody was ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, I was the player manager and I stayed that way for some time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Was it a little awkward being a player and then being elevated above your fellows like that?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was the same Charlie Grimm as I was when I was playing for the other managers.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one thing I believe that where I was a little successful, I was one of the guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't change at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe it was a strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was.
[SPEAKER_02]: Woody English, he was on that team.
[SPEAKER_02]: He lives about a hundred miles from us.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a couple of real nice interviews with Woody.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is his boat, Mudder's boat.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was a great infield.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a great infield and a good ballclub.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course that Wilson, you know, he drove in 190 runs and I don't think that record will ever be broken.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't care how much rabbit they put in the ball at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was 1930.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he was very fortunate then.
[SPEAKER_01]: because he had those guys like Hartnett and Kyler and Stevenson getting on base every time they went to bat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course he had the good bat to drive them in.
[SPEAKER_02]: How come Wilson had that one really great year as well?
[SPEAKER_02]: Never before after he quite matched Hunter?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well a lot of people said that a drink got him but I don't think it did.
[SPEAKER_01]: He came out to that ballpark every day to play.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't misjudge a guy for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you have any trouble managing him?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all, not at all, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he should have lasted, this girl should have lasted longer than it did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he had the tools, he was just adequate defensively, just an average runner, but he could swing that bat.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about that 29 World Series?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that was a series of surprises because I don't know where Connie Mack had Howard Emke warming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wasn't on the ball field because Grove was warming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether he warmed up or not, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't throw hard, I'll say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he threw a lot of those screwballs up there, something we were all figuring on hitting against Grove.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when Emke walked out of there,
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody grabbed a bat and said, oh I want to hit against that guy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the bat boy picked up a bat.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he got us.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the second time around he didn't have it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was Connie Mack's genius.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was the ball game where they just were red hot when they had that 10 run inning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That must have been unbelievable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, third time Jimmy Fox went around Third Base.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told him I was going to trip him if he'd come around again.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got sick and tired of him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what about the trade to Chicago?
[SPEAKER_02]: How did that go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Admiral Wilbur Cooper and myself went over there for Dick Niehaus, George Grantham,
[SPEAKER_01]: And Vic Aldridge, a right-hand pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Moranville and Cooper didn't last long, and I just stayed there until the end of my career.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, you left the team to go and win the pennant, didn't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tony Bush went in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't play for Tony.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did this disturb you going to Chicago?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm tickled to death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just to go to Chicago to get out of Pittsburgh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, I...
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, I didn't like to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I played regular on the Pittsburgh ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I like Chicago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Paul Parson.
[SPEAKER_02]: I noticed here.
[SPEAKER_01]: The last place ball club, and I figured that I'd have a pretty good chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: How you doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Very good, thanks.
[SPEAKER_02]: I noticed here that your home run output dropped off somewhat when you went over to Chicago.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I went over there, and they start pitching out away from me, and I just
[SPEAKER_01]: hit the ball where it was pitched, my power was left center.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I was a pull hitter in Pittsburgh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pittsburgh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they had a low fence there, chicken wire in front of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I wasn't ever a home run hitter, power hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hit the ball where they pitched, get a ball inside, pull it to right field, and out away from me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had power in the left center.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you have any pitchers you didn't like to bat against?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, Dutch Ruther.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't have much trouble with any lefty.
[SPEAKER_01]: I played every day, but Dutch Ruther was a menace to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hit a little foul off of him one day,
[SPEAKER_01]: called time, come in and walked in, and Bill Clem was the umpire, and he said, well Dutch, what do you want?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, I don't want to talk to you, Bill.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, I want to talk to Graham.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, well, what do you want to talk to me for?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, I just want to let you know that you're going down on the next pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's going to dust me off on the next pitch because I got that foul off him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a good guy.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a great pitcher, Dutch Ruthridge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you ever get hit in the head by anybody?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yeah, Carl Hummel hit me one day.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no brushback pitches.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you were dusted off, you were knocked down.
[SPEAKER_01]: There were some pretty mean guys in the league.
[SPEAKER_01]: What were their names?
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite a few of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Joe Escher,
[SPEAKER_01]: There was one old Joe out of Philadelphia, Philly's.
[SPEAKER_01]: Van Lingle, Mungo, when he got mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: An old Dodger pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite a few of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was a couple on every pitch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did Parmer ever hit you?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a little bit too wild to throw at you.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hits you unintentionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't feel too free out there when he was pitching.
[SPEAKER_02]: I talked to him one day, and it's been a couple of hours with him.
[SPEAKER_02]: He hit five batters in the head in his career.
[SPEAKER_02]: And after each time this has happened, they had to take him out of the game.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was the days before the helmet, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, they call them brushback pitches.
[SPEAKER_01]: They tipped you over.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there any spitballers still pitching when you were?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, oh yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Willie Grimes, Phil Douglas.
[SPEAKER_01]: They throw a few now, too, don't think they don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're legal then now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about Hornby as a manager?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, a lot of ballplayers didn't get along with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got along with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as you were delivering and hustling for him, it didn't make any difference how good you were going or how bad you were going.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't say anything to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was strictly a loner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never patted anybody on the back, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: He expected every ballplayer, he was very much like Ty Cobb.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ty Cobb expected every ball player that played for him to be as good as he was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hornby was very much, as far as hitting was concerned, he expected everybody in his lineup to hit as good as he hit, and that was an impossibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody could do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he was a great right-hand hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he stayed completely away.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no discussions or anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: in the clubhouse with any of his ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd come in, take his uniform off, go to the hotel, and that was it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See him the next day at the ballpark.
[SPEAKER_02]: They say if he saw anybody with newspaper in there, he'd take it away from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't allow any smoking in the clubhouse, the newspaper.
[SPEAKER_02]: Must have been a real change when you took over.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it was.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was.
[SPEAKER_01]: I turned them loose.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of the team wasn't the best.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got along fine with Rog.
[SPEAKER_02]: He loved the ponies, didn't he?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to a great extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how much, whether he won on them or what, but... Well, the 32 World Series.
[SPEAKER_02]: Was that four straight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Four straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never come close.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about that called shot by the Bay?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the only one guy that was under the gun.
[SPEAKER_01]: Harden said he didn't
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course he pointed out toward the mound and when he was pointing he talked to Guy Bush.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gabby said that Guy Bush was yelling at Ruth and Ruth stepped down the batter's box and he pointed out toward the mound and he says, you'll be out there tomorrow, see what you can do with me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello Shelly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: He stepped in the batter's box and
[SPEAKER_01]: Root's next pitch, boom, out of the ballpark.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he let it lay.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a great man, Root was.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was gone and everything, and he just let it lay where it was.
[SPEAKER_02]: How did you work your pitching rotation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Any particular plan?
[SPEAKER_01]: I had four.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had Larry French, Bill Lee, Charlie Root, Sheriff Blake.
[SPEAKER_01]: I used my starting pitchers once in a while in the jam, like Bill Lee with the good curveball, or Larry French with the screwball.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I needed a pitcher for an inning, I'd send him down there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pitching one inning didn't stop him in those days, starting pitchers.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't have middle relievers and late relievers?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the years we won 21 straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Talk about that stuff and all about that ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a great ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time they left that club out, boy I'll tell you, they went out to win.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course they got every conceivable break.
[SPEAKER_01]: They made a lot of breaks themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they won on the other club's mistakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kick one or a bad joke.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boom.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say there's an opening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go through being in nine times out of ten.
[SPEAKER_01]: They came through Yeah, that's right Yeah, let's say it just like the newspaper man after the one or 18th straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: We were all up in the clubhouse and Everybody was jubilant, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything else went in 18th straight came a knock on the door and a young
[SPEAKER_01]: The sports writer was at the door and Andy Lacho came over to the locker room and said, there's a young man, a sports writer there, he's got a pencil on a pad.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, I'd like to interview you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you're in good humor after you win 18 straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, let him come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sit down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I even dusted off a chair in front of my locker and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: His first question was, well, how's the team going?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there was a lull there for a minute and he was out on a ramp.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't answer the question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you let the reporters in after games?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yeah, the tour was off.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always figured this, that sportswriters were part of the games just like myself and anybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one thing I always did say with my sportswriters, or our sportswriters, when I said this was off the record, they believed me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they did.
[SPEAKER_01]: They never had any trouble.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they never, all they do is they have the liberty of going around the clubhouse talking to the ballplayers and whatever they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: In those days.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ed Burns?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ed Burns, Irving Vaughn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who was that fellow, Hugh Fullerton?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, he was a special assignment man, Hugh Fulton.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember him.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I remember Ring Lardner and all those fellows.
[SPEAKER_02]: You gave him plenty of stories, haven't you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ring Lardner's about the only guy, he used to sit on our bench.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sat on the bench with McGraw, too, while the game was going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just sit there and he didn't know you and never hear a peep out of him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't go up to the press box on ball games.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ask if he could sit down and the next morning you'd see the doggone story in a paper he never told you what.
[SPEAKER_02]: How about the umpires?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I got along with the umpires, great shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bill Clem, Zye Furman, Bob Bensley, all the old timers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hank O'Day, Jock O'Connor, they were all great umpires.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when they only had two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, earlier they only had one in the old days.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, way back.
[SPEAKER_02]: O'Day was umpiring back in the early days and they had only one umpire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that was a little before my time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Players used to cut second base because the umpire couldn't see everywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now they have four and six and some of the big names.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the game has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has changed a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: I go around sometimes to Kiwanis and Rotary Club and things like that, and the number one question, I have a question and answer program, and the number one thing is, don't you wish you were in your prime today instead of when you play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody asks me why, I say there's too much confusion now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we had any differences to iron out with anybody on the ball club, we'd go upstairs with the club owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Walk right in the door and lay it on the table.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, newspaper men find out and everybody, fans find out before anybody else finds out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ball players are fighting with the manager on the bench and oh my god, everything's happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tough managing today.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Confusion is terrible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did P.K.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrigley take over?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did his father die about that time when you became the manager?
[SPEAKER_02]: How is he as an owner?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he was a great man.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think baseball is going to miss him.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't miss him yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hasn't been gone in a great long amount of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's done a lot for baseball and a lot for a lot of ballplayers that nobody knows anything about.
[SPEAKER_01]: A wonderful man.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all he ever thought about was for the fans.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was interested in fans being comfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the other thing was security for his ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_02]: I like his idea of keeping lights out of the field.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always seemed like a daytime game.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think that his boy will follow his footsteps, Bill.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just like his dad.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were in 35 when you won the penalty.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was Cabrera's first year, was it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was quite a youthful star.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was something.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's the best young ball player that I've seen in my whole career.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean just
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, Mickey Maddow, he came to the American League.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been in the National League all my life.
[SPEAKER_01]: The best young ball player that just came out of high school from the very first day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, he spent one year in Peoria in the old three-eye league.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when he come back, he was ready.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you benched yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had it all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did he need a lot of coaching?
[SPEAKER_02]: I coached at third base.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you ever earn any much?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had a coach at, heck, it was a name in a high school.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't think of it now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lane Tech?
[SPEAKER_01]: Lane Tech, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't think of his name now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just was going to say his name.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he took a ball player, a kid.
[SPEAKER_01]: taught him the fundamentals.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he came in a professional baseball, he knew.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knew.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cabaretta was one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: What they wanted to do was make a pitcher out of him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I insisted on the first baseman.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had good hands, a good bat.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had to play every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wanted to pitch one day and rest three days.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wanted to just bat in that ballgame.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you were a great boy, you didn't last long as a manager yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's one of the things I think that I was very disappointed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought he'd make a good man.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't delve into the thing to find out what was wrong or anything, but they say he just couldn't
[SPEAKER_01]: make contact with the players.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was hot-headed.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a hot-headed boy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he belongs in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's now batting coach for the Mets, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but a fine boy.
[SPEAKER_02]: How'd you feel about hanging him up yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't think any ballplayer feels good about that, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But after I stayed around
[SPEAKER_01]: in the game, just like I am now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm partly in the game.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out here with the instructional league in the fall of the year, and out here with the big club when they train out here.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the Cubs, are you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I keep in contact with things going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lou Fonseca's still tied to the Cubs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he's the batting coach.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's doing a great job.
[SPEAKER_01]: When do you first hang them out for you, that first year?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a little empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to stay out of there because they'll soon forget you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I got right back in there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you hit .296 in .34.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Played about half the season.
[SPEAKER_02]: I had a bad back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Was that haste in your exit then, the back?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was one of them in .35.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I was so glad to see Cattarelli.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who played first place the other part of the year, 34, do you have?
[SPEAKER_01]: We had a guy by the name of Tolson from Los Angeles.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had a triple A ball from his last Los Angeles thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had quite a few others.
[SPEAKER_02]: I expect one of the toughest jobs as a manager is in the spring training cut-down time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I'm not afraid of all the young players.
[SPEAKER_02]: Especially with the young fellas.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you tell them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you've got to sit down with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a tough job.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because once they smell that extra money, that extra meal money, and live in the best of hotels, you know, it's pretty hard to make that approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: But baseball now is a little more refined than the minor leagues, like AAA golf, or AA and A.
[SPEAKER_01]: They travel pretty good, and the meal money's good,
[SPEAKER_01]: All they got to do is keep an incentive up in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't let them get their dobbers down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if I let them fight till we're back, there's only one place to play, and that's the major leagues.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can always come back up here.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you hadn't managed, would you have played any minor league ball after your big league days?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, age was, you've got to consider your age.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't have gone there, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: How about 38?
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the year Gabby took over, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, he took over in July.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when my back was really on the bone.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when I told her I never was fired in those two years, never fired.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went out there on my own steam.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you suggest Gabby?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never knew the disappointment for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when Gabby had been a good manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wanted to penetrate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what the hell happened either.
[SPEAKER_02]: He stayed on for three or four years.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'll tell you, the only advice I can give a young fellow is, of course, like I say, I was the most fortunate guy in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I've seen it happen to so many ballplayers that stayed right in the major leagues and
[SPEAKER_01]: managed the same ball club they played for and didn't make it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think a guy's got to go get some experience in the minor leagues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particularly in these days.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've got to know your ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the ones that are coming up are the ones you've got to know too.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just like you down there, they're no less just like you up here.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're going to be skeptical of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you mean when you said you thought you were the luckiest ball player?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I came to a ball club that didn't have a first baseman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I was traded over to Chicago that didn't have a first baseman.
[SPEAKER_01]: And played regular right on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you took over a team and contention.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've got to get those kind of breaks and you've got to realize how lucky you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: How about injuries?
[SPEAKER_01]: and a broken finger and a broken leg.
[SPEAKER_01]: In real good shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: The back problem was as much as it had in your career?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, not anymore, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean during your career, that was the only thing that really got to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: What I'm trying to get at is any injuries during your career and it doesn't look like you missed out on the 35 seasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that was the end of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's quite a
[SPEAKER_02]: A record of good health.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you play hurt any?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to be 80 years old.
[SPEAKER_01]: I figure he's catching up with me a little bit now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bleeding ulcer and all this stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did you do after you left the Cubs at 38?
[SPEAKER_01]: Bill Beck and I owned the old Milwaukee Brewers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bill Beck Jr. now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we bought that club.
[SPEAKER_02]: How'd you get together with him?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, through Mr. Wrigley.
[SPEAKER_01]: We went up there and won a little world championship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, Bill Beckett, to me, is the world's greatest promoter in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one thing, with all his promotion, he has a good ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll bet my right hand
[SPEAKER_01]: But in a year, he's going to have a good ball club there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's going to have a good ball club there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be 1979.
[SPEAKER_02]: What he did in Cleveland was something I'll never forget.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was in Cleveland.
[SPEAKER_02]: He shared that feeling that gripped the whole city as he began to build up interest and a ball club.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you were up, you managed the Milwaukee team for around three years?
[SPEAKER_01]: I managed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, when I went back to the Cubs in 44, went back to the Cubs in 44, and then we won in 45, I had to sell my stock in AAA because you couldn't own stock in a minor league ball club and manage a major league club.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that a new rule?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, wow.
[SPEAKER_02]: They gave you about a year or so to sell?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you took over in 44 when they were in 8th place, and they finished 4th.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what'd you do to them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in 45, I was out with a whole bunch of guys, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: They knew how to play ball.
[SPEAKER_02]: Was Donald Sander over there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, Jim Donald.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've talked with him over in Indianapolis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good guy.
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, a lot of power for a little guy like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, he's a good boss.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, uh, 45, that was, uh, uh, Detroit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you win by much that year?
[SPEAKER_02]: 18?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, we, we went right on.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a great year in baseball, 45.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relived all those, Derringer and all those guys, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: They went over with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No meetings, they knew what to do with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's your biggest thrill?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: I always, always, always stand up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pulling in that gate of a major league ballplayer was always a thrill to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put that major league uniform away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But playing in the World Series, I think, is the biggest thrill a guy can get.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's the biggest thrill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you play in the World Series, you want to play in another one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I hit a home run.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hit a home run off of Jack Quinn in the 29th series.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the ball game he lost when he scored those 10 runs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a thrill to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just love, there's just not enough ball players like Pete Rose.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll make a believer out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no fault in this about what he does.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've seen him play too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: A lot of guys say, well, they have
[SPEAKER_01]: He's a showman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure he's a showman.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the way he plays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get out of my way.
[SPEAKER_01]: His name's Ty Cobb.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say Ty Cobb is brutal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, he had a terrible day.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ty Cobb was alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody wanted to work with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a mean man.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's this guy here.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's got a sense of humor and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's rolling.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's a good copy.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said he would play golf.
[SPEAKER_02]: He loved to play golf.
[SPEAKER_02]: He wanted you to play for nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, sir.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he went and fell out for $385,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: He couldn't say that story anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about playing an old Baker ball?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, that was something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you ever get anybody thrown out of first base from right field?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I played ball there.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the years I played in the National League, when we played in the Becker's Bowl, I haven't hit that bar of soap yet on that right field fence.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've had a bar of soap, sir?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I had a big sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember one time, Nugent, Jerry Nugent, who owned the club.
[SPEAKER_01]: Evidently, they just left the gate open or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was always something going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had a big sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: Phillies use Lifebuoy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some guy got in there with a paintbrush and said, they should because they stink.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jesus, that thing stood on like a sore thumb when the fans come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we had a very funny fellow on our ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: His name was Cotton Tierney.
[SPEAKER_01]: He always said they had a little concession stand there and they could bowl.
[SPEAKER_01]: They used to have hot dogs on a tray and a little guy, a punch-drunk fighter, he used to go around and around, all around the stand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said there was never a fly downtown there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're all out at Bakers Farm following this guy with that tray of hot dogs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then more funny things happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where Dick Spalding, an outfitter, pigeons used to roost in the scoreboard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it had a scoreboard that went up from the ground up on the right center field fence, and the pitchers used to, and Fred, well, no, Fred Louderis, the first baseman, and Carson Bigby, Carson Bigby, he was a line driver.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dick Spalding was playing center field, and it was a brand new ball.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he hit this brand new ball as I fly up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Spalding was running over there for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It had gotten the sun somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it hit the scoreboard and a pigeon flew up.
[SPEAKER_01]: He saw that white thing and he ran after that goddamn pigeon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So help me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he turned around, went right in the clubhouse and never played another ball game.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here's the ball laying by the scoreboard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Scared that pigeon out of him, he ran after the pigeon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why didn't he play another game?
[SPEAKER_02]: He's embarrassed?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, he quit.
[SPEAKER_02]: That happened.
[SPEAKER_02]: He quit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just went right into the clubhouse.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could throw people out from right field on a ground ball.
[SPEAKER_01]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_02]: You could throw them out at first on a ground ball.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once in a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once Klein did it a lot of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particularly off pitchers.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where Cline had all his home runs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ted Williams.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not Ted, but... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did Cline come over to you in 32?
[SPEAKER_02]: Who?
[SPEAKER_02]: Cline.
[SPEAKER_02]: Didn't Cline come over to the Cubs in 32?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Didn't his home run output fall way down?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, God, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nobody knew what a terrible defensive ball player he was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all he had to do was stand there by that fence, and what the hell.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you could let the ball go over the damn thing every time, where else?
[SPEAKER_02]: Back up against it and come out and get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody knew if he could go back or forward on the fly ball or anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: You found out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: How about the polo grounds?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that sure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a lopsided ballpark to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could pop them in the left field or right field.
[SPEAKER_02]: Chinese home runs.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in center field of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: A lot of good ballgames though in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great ball clubs there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Paul McGrath, McGraw.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you know McGrath?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did you think of him as a man again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he was a great man.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had the reputation of being a rough and tumble guy.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He loved his ball class.
[SPEAKER_01]: They knew it too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Might be fresh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come along.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here we are.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where are we?
[SPEAKER_03]: This is Thursday morning, June 15th, 1978.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're on the road to L.A.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about 6.30 in the morning.
[SPEAKER_03]: We left Phoenix, or Mesa, where we spent a couple of days.
[SPEAKER_03]: At quarter after five,
[SPEAKER_03]: had bumper-to-bumper traffic practically all the way out to this interstate 10, some 40 or 50 miles west of Phoenix.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now we're on the interstate.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's just nothing ahead but vast, endless spaces.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we thought we'd put on the tape the comments from the Thornton Lee interview of yesterday.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yesterday morning at Lee's house out in Phoenix.
[SPEAKER_03]: I got there about 10 and left about 2.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was a very good interview.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was an interview we almost didn't have because I tried to get Jock O'Conlon as my second interview in Phoenix.
[SPEAKER_03]: He was tied up for the next couple of days, unable to see me.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we went to Thornton Lee, who was quite agreeable.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so it turned out to be a very good thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, we arrived there about 10 at schedule, although it was
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe a little after 10.
[SPEAKER_03]: We didn't have too much trouble finding the house.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we were greeted pleasantly by Thornton Lee and Mrs. Lee, and were ushered into the living room and chatted briefly and set up the recorder.
[SPEAKER_03]: The interview lasted about two and a half hours.
[SPEAKER_03]: We could have had more on there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But we ran into the lunch hour, and that
[SPEAKER_03]: curtailed things briefly and I got a little bit more on after the lunch hour when we were looking through the scrapbook.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know how well that picked up some of his remarks there because you're some distance from the recorder.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now what about the house?
[SPEAKER_03]: Outside and in, would you say?
[SPEAKER_03]: It was a nice house.
[SPEAKER_00]: It went into a hallway.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you went into a hallway, and on the right was the living room.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the left was the dining room.
[SPEAKER_00]: And from the dining room, as you were standing there on the left, was the kitchen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the back way went out into the another room in the patio.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was a hallway off the dining room.
[SPEAKER_00]: It led to bedrooms and a huge bath.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then there was another bath off the kitchen.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've lived in the house more than 40 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they had the bathroom all remodeled.
[SPEAKER_00]: The kitchen is all remodeled with a big freezer and a refrigerator.
[SPEAKER_00]: How old the house did you say it was?
[SPEAKER_00]: I imagine it was probably new when they got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Around 40, 45 years ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's well kept.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the furniture that it came from, they got when they were in Chicago from the Chicago Furniture Mart.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good furniture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a lovely home.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is.
[SPEAKER_03]: A lot of books around.
[SPEAKER_03]: He does a lot of reading.
[SPEAKER_03]: And a book by Leon Uras in the living room is reading mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's trying to get rid of things now.
[SPEAKER_00]: She gives a lot to their daughter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a two-story house?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, one-story house.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it much yard behind?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's a small lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all walled in with big smith block wall.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so they really can't grow much out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has grape vines growing on a patio that he built out in the back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he has a couple of orange trees and a couple of avocado trees.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he has a few tomatoes that probably won't come to much, she said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they have a big brick patio attached to the back of the house that he built.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one whole wall, and the wall must be six foot high or more.
[SPEAKER_00]: About 25, 30 feet long in one place.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's stacked solid with cut wood that he goes out and cuts himself, logs.
As I say, it's air-cooled and air-conditioned, both.
Refrigerated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Apparently they have these little fans at the top of the house that bring air in and then it goes through a refrigeration unit and cools the house.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's cheaper to run than the air conditioner.
[SPEAKER_00]: They call it refrigeration.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refrigerated air.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I thought it was an air conditioner at first, but it's different.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was quite comfortable when we were there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all she had was the refrigerator.
[SPEAKER_00]: refrigerated air on but they do have air conditioning but they have air conditioning because the refrigerated air actually works as well if not better but it doesn't work in a storm apparently they have to shut those vans back there or someplace whatever it is and uh so they they use their air conditioning there but for the most part they just use their
[SPEAKER_00]: refrigerated air.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's a very, very attractive woman.
Busy, busy, busy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Looks like nasty gossip to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, she doesn't, she's no suntan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cause she's never out in the sun.
[SPEAKER_00]: And uh,
[SPEAKER_00]: They both come from large families.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, at least they both have relatives.
[SPEAKER_00]: Brothers and sisters.
[SPEAKER_00]: She has a sister and one of them has a sister in Yosemite with a beautiful home there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then she has a sister in San Jacinto.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another relative had just moved to Phoenix or thereabouts in that general area.
[SPEAKER_00]: Her son was over and had lunch with us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And their son is in Tucson now as a coach.
[SPEAKER_00]: He used to coach at Arizona State.
[SPEAKER_00]: He coached in a college for four years.
[SPEAKER_00]: All Thornton Lee's family are school teachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: She has a sister still living in Lowell.
[SPEAKER_00]: or wherever in a way she grew up.
[SPEAKER_03]: From what I had known and my impressions of Thornton Lee as a ballplayer, he was the mediocre pitcher who won really good year in 1941.
[SPEAKER_03]: But of course, he was with Cleveland in those early years, the 30s and 90s.
[SPEAKER_03]: I saw him and read about him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He never realized his great promise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Connie Mack once said he was going to be another lefty pro, but he never quite made it.
[SPEAKER_00]: She kept talking about a Venus star.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I never got the impression of much of a personality for Lee.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just never had any run-ins with the management or the outliers.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just seemed to be quiet, minding his own business.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not very good news copy.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you just got the impression he was kind of a quiet person who didn't do much or think much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yet, so that was one reason I wasn't really excited about having an interview with him.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seemed like he wouldn't have much to say.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it quickly became apparent in this interview that he was a very intelligent, perceptive, and articulate man.
[SPEAKER_03]: I couldn't quite get whether he went to four years of college at Cal Poly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, he did.
[SPEAKER_03]: years he was there then, I didn't quite get that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He must have finished up at 26 when he had been about 20 years old then.
[SPEAKER_03]: He may have finished after he started playing ball.
[SPEAKER_03]: He picked up things very quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had all kinds of letters in that while he was in college.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he must have been in every sport.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because she had all those pictures in one envelope of all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he went to a military school before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a boy's school is where he went.
[SPEAKER_00]: More like a prep school.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they went back to Sonoma.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know whether it was their son or not, went to that New Mexico Military Institute for a nephew or somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he went to an all-boys school, or prep school.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was very impressed by him.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when I explained what I wanted to do and how to do it, he brought on right away, went right along with it, beautifully tracing the family history.
[SPEAKER_03]: Semi-pro day, minor league career in that year, 1929, where he was with Globe in the New Mexico State League, or the Arizona-New Mexico League.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, did he tell you how he got there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, he did, but I forgot what he said.
[SPEAKER_00]: About the, wherever they were playing, or whoever they were with, he and I'm sure she said Lefty Gomez were the pitchers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tony Freitas.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought you said Lefty Gomez.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I've got down here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, there was a doubleheader, and whichever one lost would be sent to Globe to play.
[SPEAKER_03]: I didn't get that story, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who would he have been playing for?
[SPEAKER_00]: What team would that have been?
[SPEAKER_00]: He would have been up with them in spring practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, San Francisco Shields.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whichever one lost the game would be sent
[SPEAKER_00]: to Globe and the manager, whoever it was at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I want to say Dykes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want you to doubt it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They both won.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said whoever lost would be sent to Globe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we lost one to nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the other pitcher won.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so he went to Globe.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was sent down to Globe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where he met her in Globe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they got married.
[SPEAKER_03]: What did she do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did she tell you how they met or anything?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, she just said they met in Globe.
[SPEAKER_03]: She was from Miami, though.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is a short distance from Globe.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know, but they consider it Globe, apparently.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's been a rivalry between the two teams.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's how she met him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how they got married.
[SPEAKER_03]: They got married that winter after that 29th season.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the depression structure.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a good account of how the Depression just wrecked that lake.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because all the miners went out of work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, and there's the Monty Stratton story.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had the gun strapped to his leg when it went off and he lost his leg?
[SPEAKER_03]: Something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, well they were very, very close.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, he has pictures of Monty Stratton's wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think he had two children then or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were both babies.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she has pictures of the children as they grow up, the strapped kids.
[SPEAKER_00]: But apparently, Monty Stratton wanted a gun very badly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so we bought him one and told him how to use it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he went out this day, honey, with a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It strapped on his leg and it went off.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is how he lost his leg.
[SPEAKER_00]: She said it took Lee quite a while to get over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I told you about his woodpile, that he chops wood for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He also makes bread.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they get a lot of stuffed produce from friends, and he cans.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he goes out as a friend and gets the raisins and makes raisins, and boy, were they good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Best raisins I've ever tasted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Big, plump, juicy ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they have to be kept refrigerated all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he pickles fakes, among other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when they were in Cleveland, did he tell you they lived in O'Neal's house?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because Mrs. O'Neal took the kids to Scranton.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so they were very fortunate in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they've kept up with the O'Neill family.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, they're still quite close.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Kennedy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, Kennedy is owner of what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Was owner of what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Kennedy is the general manager of the Chicago Cubs.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK. Not Kennedy.
[SPEAKER_03]: The teammate of his is the Chicago Whitesides.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's who he scouts for, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: The Cubs?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the Cardinals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, he's with the Cardinals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Charlie goes with the Cubs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it was through Kennedy that she said he got the scouting job because he had always wanted to be a scout and couldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Kennedy came and they moved to Phoenix.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was through him they got it because she said they always keep the scouting jobs kind of in the family or for their friends and that because they get a salary plus expenses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Red Zillner's son is the scout for Cincinnati out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's always coming over to get tips on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she said he has that Denny that's up now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, John Denny in Chicago.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Denny's got two or three more players in Class A.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they say that he writes the best scouting reports out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if there's a real hot prospect, they'll call him to go and look at him because he's so good at analyzing pictures and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd believe that.
[SPEAKER_03]: know his business very well.
[SPEAKER_00]: They said he could just scout, everything else and so if it's a real hot prospect that's what they do because he sends in these scouting reports and of course some scouts never find anybody but he seems to have a talent for spotting them
[SPEAKER_00]: And their son, Don, is a son who is also a pitcher, just starting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And his grandpa thinks that they may have the third big league player in the family.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I think he's only 15.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you got the story of the son, who won Rookie of the Year when he was with the Senators.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then with the Astros, and then with the Detroit, and he looks just like his father.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you want to tell about the Marty Kennedy story and the Dutch Reader?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: When he was, when Lee was with the Giants last year in 47 or so, he had hooked on with the Giants by talking to them a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: They trained out here.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know what it was, but he dropped out.
[SPEAKER_03]: They pitched a couple of games in exhibition, I guess, and they signed him up on the only stage after the season, and they let him go.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they had a young pitcher, Monty Kennedy.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Giants did, and Lee spent a lot of time working with him out in the bullpen, giving him instructions.
[SPEAKER_03]: firing questions at him, how he would react in certain situations, and Kennedy was very good.
[SPEAKER_03]: He always knew just how to react, always had the right responses to situations.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then when he got in a game, he forgot everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: It went right out of his head.
[SPEAKER_03]: He didn't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a U-Wallet up there, and another car dragging a car.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're just poking along at about 70, so we better go by them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not really.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think they're moving.
[SPEAKER_03]: About 60.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a U-Wallet in front, and a small U-Wallet behind it.
[SPEAKER_03]: They must be coming west.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know where they're from.
[SPEAKER_03]: I forgot what it was like.
Illinois.
Now, uh,
[SPEAKER_03]: You can see it along the way here about seven minutes before seven on this bright, sunny day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sun's beginning to burn down already.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's even seven o'clock.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, Kennedy didn't remember much when he got out there, did he?